Julius W. Becton Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Julius W. Becton Papers 1780-2008 1951-2008
MSS85425
Becton, Julius W. (Julius Wesley), 1926-2023
69,300 items
198 containers plus 8 oversize and 21 classified
79.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Army officer, federal agency head, university president, public school superintendent. Correspondence, speeches, writings, military and civilian government documents, topical files, reports, printed matter, monographs, and miscellaneous material documenting Becton's army career, leadership of federal agencies, college presidency, and superintendency of a large, urban public school system.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Ackerman, Arlene C., 1947-2013--Correspondence.; Becton, Julius W. (Julius Wesley), 1926-2023--Family.; Becton, Julius W. (Julius Wesley), 1926-2023.; Becton, Julius W. (Julius Wesley), 1926-2023. Becton: autobiography of a soldier and public servant. 2008.; Berry, Sidney B. (Sidney Bryan), 1926-2013--Correspondence.; Brimmer, Andrew F.--Correspondence.; Brooks, Harry W.--Correspondence.; Brooks, Leo A., Jr., 1957- --Correspondence.; Bush, George, 1924-2018.; Clarke, Bruce C. (Bruce Cooper), 1901-1988--Correspondence.; Crain, Jonathan, 1755-1820.; Dickerson, Harvey G., Jr., 1926- --Correspondence.; Dillard, Oliver W., Sr., 1926-2015--Correspondence.; Francis, H. Minton, Sr., 1922-2014--Correspondence.; Goldsborough, Edmund L. (Edmund Lee), III, 1939- --Correspondence.; Gough, Harvey, approximately 1939- --Correspondence.; Hamilton, West A., 1886-1985--Correspondence.; Hamlet, James F.--Correspondence.; Higgins, Chester A., Sr., 1917-2000--Correspondence.; Hooks, Benjamin L. (Benjamin Lawson), 1925-2010--Correspondence.; King, John Q. Taylor (John Quill Taylor), 1921-2011--Correspondence.; Lord, Sharon B.--Correspondence.; MacLaury, Bruce K.--Correspondence.; Moskos, Charles C.--Correspondence.; Nabors, Robert L.--Correspondence.; Otis, Glenn K.--Correspondence.; Patton, George S. (George Smith), IV, 1923-2004--Correspondence.; Powell, Colin L.--Correspondence.; Reagan, Ronald.; Robinson, Roscoe, Jr., 1928-1993--Correspondence.; Rogers, Bernard William--Correspondence.; Rogers, Charles C. (Charles Calvin), 1929-1990--Correspondence.; Rommel, Manfred, 1928-2013--Correspondence.; Shoemaker, Robert M. (Robert Morin), 1924- --Correspondence.; Stockman, Hervey S., 1922- 2011--Correspondence.; Weber, La Vern E., 1923-1999--Correspondence.; Wickham, John Adams, 1928- --Correspondence.
Organizations
Association of the United States Army.; George C. Marshall Foundation.; Institute for Defense Analyses.; Lower Merion High School.; Manchu Association.; National War College (U.S.); Ninth & Tenth (Horse) Cavalry Association.; Non-commissioned Officers Association.; North Atlantic Treaty Organization.; Prairie View A & M University.; Public Schools of the District of Columbia.; Rocks (Organization); Second Division Association.; Southwest Association of Buffalo Soldiers.; United States Armor Association.; United States Army Training Center, Infantry (Fort Dix, N.J.); United States. Agency for International Development. Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance.; United States. Army Operational Test and Evaluation Agency.; United States. Army Training and Doctrine Command.; United States. Army--African American troops.; United States. Army--Officer efficiency reports.; United States. Army--Officers.; United States. Army. Airborne Division, 101st.; United States. Army. Armored Division, 2nd.; United States. Army. Cavalry Division, 1st.; United States. Army. Corps, 7th.; United States. Army. Infantry Division, 2nd.; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 9th (1855-1957); United States. Army. Parachute Infantry Regiment, 555th.; United States. Army. Tank Battalion, 761st.; United States. Continental Army.; United States. Federal Emergency Management Agency.
Subjects
African American generals.; African American soldiers--Societies, etc.; African American soldiers--West (U.S.); African American soldiers.; African American universities and colleges--Texas.; African American veterans--Societies, etc.; African American veterans.; African Americans--Education.; African Americans--History.; Civil defense.; Disaster relief--United States.; Discrimination in education--United States.; Education--United States--Finance.; Education--Washington (D.C.); Emergency management--United States.; International relief.; Korean War, 1950-1953--Participation, African American.; Korean War, 1950-1953--Veterans--United States.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; Military education--United States.; Public schools--Washington (D.C.)--Administration.; Race relations.; Veterans--United States.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Participation, African American.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; World War, 1914-1918--Participation, African American.; World War, 1914-1918--Veterans--United States.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945--Participation, African American.; World War, 1939-1945--Veterans--United States.; World War, 1939-1945.
Places
Bryn Mawr (Pa.)--Social life and customs.; United States--Armed Forces--African Americans.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Defenses.; United States--History, Military.; United States--Race relations.; West (U.S.)--History, Military--19th century.
Occupations
Administrators.; Army officers.; College presidents.; Public officials.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Julius W. Becton were given to the Library of Congress by Becton in 2008.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Thirteen caricatures/cartoons have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. One map has been transferred to the Geography and Map Division. A newspaper has been transferred to the Serial and Government Publications Division. One 16mm film reel and fifty-eight videocassettes have been transferred to the Moving Image Section of the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division (MBRS). Sixteen tape reels have been transferred to the Recorded Sound Section of MBRS. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Julius W. Becton Papers. Patrons are encouraged to contact these divisions in advance of a research visit.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Julius W. Becton are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
National Security Classified Information
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified materials.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1926, June 29 Born, Bryn Mawr, Pa.
1944, June Graduated, Lower Merion High School, Ardmore, Pa.
1943-1944 Enlisted, United States Army Air Corps Enlisted Reserve and entered active duty as a private, Keesler Air Force Base, Biloxi, Miss.
1944, Dec.-1945, Aug. Officer Candidate School, Fort Benning, Ga.
1945, Aug. 16 Commissioned a second lieutenant of Infantry, United States Army
1945, Oct.-Dec. Platoon leader and executive officer, 369th Infantry Regiment, 93rd Infantry Division, Morotai, South Pacific Theater
1946 Platoon leader, 542nd Heavy Construction Company, detailed to the Signal Corps, Philippines
1947-1948 Promoted first lieutenant, Signal Corps.
1948, Jan. 29 Married Louise A. Thornton
1948 Recalled to active duty as a second lieutenant, Signal Corps, Fort Monmouth, N.J.
1949-1950 Platoon leader, 9th Infantry Regiment, 2nd Infantry Division, Fort Lewis, Wash.
1950 Platoon leader, L Company, 9th Infantry Regiment, Korea
1951 Company commander, L Company, 9th Infantry Regiment, Korea
1953 Promoted to captain, United States Army
1954-1957 Communications officer, company commander, and assistant operations officer, 2nd Armored Division, West Germany
1957-1960 Assistant professor of military science and tactics, ROTC program, Prairie View A&M University, Prairie View, Tex.
1960 B.S. in mathematics, Prairie View A&M, Prairie View, Tex.
1961 Promoted to major, United States Army
1961-1964 Assistant G-3 (operations), 4th Logistical Command, Verdun, France
1964 Promoted to lieutenant colonel, United States Army
1965-1966 Student, Institute for Defense Analysis and University of Maryland, College Park, Md.
1966 M.A. in economics, University of Maryland, College Park, Md.
1967, Aug-Nov. Commander, 2nd Squadron, 17th Cavalry Regiment, 101st Airborne Division, Fort Campbell, Ky.
1967, Dec.-1968, Nov. Commanding officer, 2nd Squadron, 17th Cavalry Regiment, 101st Airborne Division and assistant commander, 3rd Brigade, 101st Airborne Division, Vietnam
1969, July Promoted to colonel, United States Army
1969-1970 Student, National War College, Washington, D.C.
1970-1972 Commander, 2nd Brigade, 2nd Armored Division, Fort Hood, Tex.
1972, Jan.-Aug. Chief, Armor Branch, Officer Personnel Directorate, Office of Personnel Operations, United States Department of the Army
1972, Aug. Promoted to brigadier general, United States Army
1972-1975 Deputy commander, United States Army Training Center, Fort Dix, N.J.
1974, Aug. Promoted to major general, United States Army
1975-1976 Commanding general, 1st Cavalry Division, Fort Hood, Tex.
1976-1978 Commanding general, United States Army Operational Test and Evaluation Agency
1978, May Promoted to major general, United States Army
1978, Nov. Promoted to lieutenant general, United States Army
1978-1981 Commanding general, 7th Corps, United States Army Europe, Germany
1981-1983 Deputy commanding general, Training and Doctrine Command, and Army inspector general of training, Ft. Monroe, Va.
1983, Aug. Retired from the United States Army
1984-1985 Director, Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance, Agency for International Development
1985-1989 Director, Federal Emergency Management Agency
1989-1994 President, Prairie View A&M University, Prairie View, Tex.
1996-1998 Superintendent/CEO, District of Columbia Public Schools, Washington, D.C.
2008 Published Becton: Autobiography of a Soldier and Public Servant. Annapolis: Naval Institute Press
2023, Nov. 28 Died, Fort Belvoir, Va.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Julius W. Becton (1926-2023) span the years 1780-2008, with the bulk of the material dating from 1951 to 2008. The collection documents Becton's career as a United States Army officer who commanded infantry and armor in war and peace, the first African American general to command a corps, director of the Federal Emergency Management Administration during the Reagan administration, an educator and president of Prairie View A & M University in Texas, and superintendent of the District of Columbia Public Schools. The papers are primarily in English, with some German and Vietnamese. The papers are organized into twelve series: General Correspondence, Army Career, Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance, Federal Emergency Management Agency, Prairie View A & M University, District of Columbia Public Schools, Organizations, Speeches and Writings, Subject File, Miscellany, National Security Classified Information, and Oversize. Scattered documents are in German and Vietnamese.
The General Correspondence series is arranged chronologically and mainly documents Becton’s interests, activities, and friendships outside of day-to-day professional commitments. The series is mainly a product of his post-retirements from the army and from his civilian jobs, much of it retrospective, looking back at people, incidents, and issues from his working life. It also documents periods in his army career when he was between commands, on short staff stints, and matriculated at military and civilian academic institutions. Correspondents in the series include Harry W. Brooks, Edmund L. Goldsborough, Harvey Gough, Chester Higgins (1917-2000), Benjamin L. Hooks, John Q. Taylor King, Charles C. Moskos, Robert L. Nabors, Colin L. Powell, and Manfred Rommel.
The General Correspondence, though extensive, does not account for the bulk of the correspondence in the papers. Most correspondence is part of series and files related to his army commands and leadership of military agencies while on active duty; to the civilian disaster relief agencies he directed after retiring from the army, the Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance (OFDA) and the Federal Emergency Management Agency; to his presidency of Prairie View A&M University; and to his superintendency of the District of Columbia Public Schools.
The Army Career series documents Becton’s nearly forty-year career in the United States Army, from his enlistment in 1943 to his retirement as a lieutenant general (three stars) in 1983. The series is organized into files relating to his troop commands and leadership of Army agencies; an academic file relating to his stints in the armed forces graduate programs; and topical files on subjects such as race relations in the Army and the Officer Efficency Report System (OERS). Large groupings in the Army Career series include files on the 9th Infantry Division (platoon leader and company commander in combat during the Korean War, 1950-1953); 101st Airborne Division (squadron commander of the attached 17th Cavalry Regiment), and assistant brigade commander in combat in Vietnam, 1967-1968; 2nd Armored Division (brigade commander, 1970-1972); United States Army Training Center at Fort Dix, N.J. (deputy commanding general, 1972-1975); 1st Cavalry Division (commanding general, 1975-1976); Army Operational Test and Evaluation Agency (commanding general 1976-1978); 7th Corps (commanding general, 1978-1981); and the Training and Doctrine Command (deputy commanding general, 1981-1983).
Correspondents in the Army Career series include Sidney B. Berry, Harry W. Brooks, Leo A. Brooks, Bruce C. Clarke, Roscoe Robinson, Harvey G. Dickerson, H. Minton Francis, Harvey Gough, James F. Hamlet, West A. Hamilton, Chester Higgins (1917-2000), Robert C. Larson, Sharon B. Lord, Glenn K. Otis, George S. Patton (1923-2004), Charles C. Rogers, Bernard W. Rogers, Manfred Rommel, Robert M. Shoemaker, Hervey S. Stockman, La Vern E. Weber, John A. Wickham, and Oliver W. Willard,
Two series document Becton’s service in the Ronald Reagan and George Bush administrations as the director of two federal disaster relief organizations, the Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance (1984-1985), part of of the Agency for International Development, and the Federal Emergency Management Agency (1985-1989). Part of his job at FEMA was coordinating international civil defense policy by meeting regularly with counterparts from countries participating in the North Atlanic Treaty Organization. Some documents relating to this function are classified and withdrawn to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization Classified series.
From 1957 to 1960, Becton was a professor of military science and tactics in the ROTC program at Prairie View A&M University in Texas. He used this opportunity to matriculate, graduating with a BS in mathematics in 1960. In 1989 he was inaugurated as president of Prairie View A&M University, the first graduate of the school to become its president. The Prairie View A&M series documents his presidency (1989-1994) of the historically black university, and his post-presidency. A large file in the series, prepared by lawyers for the Texas A&M System, relates to Knight v. State of Alabama federal case that alleged that state property tax systems discriminated against black students by underfunding public schools and historically black institutions of higher education.
In 1996 Becton commenced what he called his “toughest challenge,” running the District of Columbia Public Schools as superintendent and CEO. The District of Columbia Public Schools series documents Becton’s tenure as school chief under the District of Columbia Financial Responsibility and Management Assistance Authority, commonly known as the Financial Control Board, or simply the Control Board. The Control Board, a five-member panel created by an act of Congress, oversaw the District's finances during 1995-2001. It had the power to override decisions of the mayor and city council. The Control Board overrode the elected school board and installed as the effective board the Emergency Transition Board of Trustees, which, in 1996, fired the superintendent and hired Becton in his place. Becton held the position until he resigned in 1998. There is frequent correspondence with Bruce E. Maclaury, chairman of of the Emergency Transition Board of Trustees. Other correspondents include Andrew Brimmer and Arlene Ackerman.
The Organizations series includes files on veterans' organizations of World War II era African American units, such as 555th Parachute Infantry Regiment and the 761st Tank Battalion; and files on the veterans and historical interest organizations of African American units that served in the American West during the aftermath of the American Civil War through the World Wars, such as the Ninth and Tenth Cavalry Association and Southwest Association of Buffalo Soldiers. While the file on the Ninth Infantry Regiment (Manchu) in which Becton served during the Korean War is part of the Army Career series, information on on the 2nd Infantry Division, which included the Ninth, is documented in the Indianhead Association file of the Organizations series. A file on the Ninth Infantry Regiment's veterans organization, the Ninth Infantry (Manchu) Association, is also part of the the Organizations series. Also in the Organizations series is a large file relating to The Rocks, an orgainization that mentors African American officer candidates and junior officers. Other professional service organizations documented in the series include the Association of the United States Army, George C. Marshall Foundation, Non-Commisioned Officers Association, and United States Armor Association. Most of these organizations are also well-documented in the General and other correspondence files.
Two major components of the Speeches and Writings series are files relating to Becton’s book, Becton: Autobiography of a Soldier and Public Servant (2008), and to his speeches. The book gestated nearly three decades resulting in several drafts. Some drafts, though unpublished, are fairly complete versions with an organization, chapter headings, anecdotes, and content that differs substantially from the published book. The speeches as a whole work the way the correspondence does, with most speeches focused on his army commands and civilian leadership positions and found within the Army Career series, and in series relating to OFDA, FEMA, Prairie View, and District of Columbia Public Schools. Speeches in Speeches and Writings are more generic and focused on his post-retirement years.
The Subject File series includes biographical material on Becton; files on his family, including correspondence and diaries; and files relating to Becton’s hometown, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, on the "Main Line" outside of Philadelphia, including files on Lower Merion High School from which he graduated. Also part of the series is material relating to African American history, particularly military history, with files on units of the pre-1950s segregated army and on the first African American general officers. The oldest in the papers, a 1780 document certifying three years of service in the Continental Army during the American Revolution of one Jonathan Cain, or Crain, is also part of the Subject File.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in twelve series:
General Correspondence, 1957-2008
Army Career, 1943-2008
Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance, 1984-2004
Federal Emergency Management Agency, 1954-2007
Prairie View A & M University, 1966-2007
District of Columbia Public Schools, 1986-2007
Organizations, 1943-2008
Speeches and Writings, 1945-2007
Subject File, 1780-2008
Miscellany, 1961-2008
National Security Classified Information, 1954-1991
Oversize, 1969-1994
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1957-2008 (Box 1-6)
  Correspondence with colleagues, friends, and members of the public, with attached material.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1957-1983 (Box 1)
  - 1984 (Box 1)
    - Jan.-Apr. (Box 1)
    - May-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1985-1986, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1987-1993, (7 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1994-1999, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - 2000-2006, (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - 2007-2008, undated, (6 folders) (Box 6)
- Army Career, 1943-2008 (Box 6-71)
  Correspondence, speeches, notes, notebooks, personnel files, unit records, academic files, scrapbooks, topical files, printed matter, government records, commissions, reports, and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged alpha-numerically by name of unit, military agency, or topic, and thereunder alpha-numerically by type of material, organization name, or topic.
  - 1st Calvary Division (Box 6)
    - Ashley, Otis H., investigation, 1976 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence (Box 6)
      - General (Box 6)
        - 1974 (Box 6)
        - 1975, (4 folders) (Box 7)
        - 1976 (Box 7)
          - Jan.-May, (2 folders) (Box 7)
          - June-Dec., undated, (7 folders) (Box 8)
      - Indexed, 1975-1976, (4 folders) (Box 9)
    - Defense Manpower Commission, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Departure from command, 1976 (Box 10)
    - Ecumenical marriage retreat, 1976 (Box 10)
    - Event programs, 1975-1976 (Box 10)
    - First Cavalry Division Association, 1976-1994 (Box 10)
    - Housing, Fort Hood, Tex., 1975-1976 (Box 10)
    - Miscellany, 1974-1989, 2003-2007 (Box 10)
    - Newspapers and newspaper clippings (Box 10)
      - Austin American-Statesman, Austin, Texas, "1st Cavalry Division honors last horse troopers, Boots and Saddles at Fort Hood," enlarged feature article, 1975, Oct. 21 See Oversize (Box 10)
      - The Cavalier, 1973 (Box 10)
      - Saber, 1976-1980 (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous, 1974-1983 (Box 11)
    - Notes, 1976-1977 (Box 11)
    - Operations manual, 1976 (Box 11)
    - Photographs, 1975, undated See also Oversize (Box 11)
    - Reading file, undated (Box 11)
    - Speeches, 1975-1976, 1989 (Box 11)
    - Speeches, 1975-1976, 1989 (Box 12)
    - Standing operating procedures (Box 12)
      - Published, 1976 (Box 12)
      - Supporting material, 1976 (Box 12)
    - Teletype messages, 1975-1976 (Box 12)
    - Visits (Box 12)
      - Camp Shelby, Miss., 1975 (Box 12)
      - Travis Air Force Base, Calif., 1976 (Box 13)
  - 2nd Armored Division (Box 13)
    - 2nd Brigade (Box 13)
      - Armor Officers Ball, 1972 (Box 13)
      - Change of command ceremonies, 1972, 1975 (Box 13)
      - Chronological file, 1970-1972, (5 folders) (Box 13)
      - "Commander's Guide to the Retention of Junior Officers," 1970 (Box 14)
      - Horn, Donald, command sergeant major, 1978-1988 (Box 14)
      - Notebooks, 1969-1972 (Box 14)
      - Printed matter, 1971-1975 (Box 14)
    - First tour, 1956-1957 (Box 15)
  - 4th Logistical Command (Box 15)
    - Bowden, James C., "Recent Developments in the Sino-Soviet Dispute," 1962 (Box 15)
    - Miscellany, 1961-1963 (Box 15)
    - "Re-enlistment Rates by Military Specialty," 1962-1963 (Box 15)
  - 7th Corps (Box 15)
    - 2nd Armored Cavalry Regiment, undated (Box 15)
    - 3rd Armored Cavalry Regiment, German-English operational dictionary, undated (Box 15)
    - Administrative requirements placed on company commanders, 1979 (Box 15)
    - Allen, James W., 2002 (Box 15)
    - American Heritage commemoration, 1981 (Box 16)
    - Armored and mechanized division operations, manual, 1978 (Box 16)
    - Army budget for fiscal year 1982, 1981 (Box 16)